Finding Aid for the George E. Palmer Papers 1937-1991
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
George E. Palmer Papers
1937-1991
1949-1981
Palmer, George E., 1908-1994.
Law professor at the University of Michigan; the collection includes lecture notes, course materials, correspondence, writings, and topical files.
9929 Aa 2
4 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The papers were donated by Julie Palmer Gzella in 1994. Donor no. 8283
The collection is open for research.
George E. Palmer was a professor of law at the University of Michigan from 1946 to 1978, when he was named professor emeritus. He was born on February 3, 1908 in Washington, Indiana, and married Ruth Hamersly on July 7, 1935. A 1932 graduate of the University of Michigan Law School, he also spent some time studying law at Columbia University around 1940. He served as attorney and associate general council for the United States Office of Price Administration from 1942 to 1945, where he authored the Rent Control Laws for the country during World War II. He was an attorney for the Department of Justice in 1945.
Palmer primarily taught courses on Trusts and Estates and Restitution while he was at the University of Michigan. He was regarded as an international authority on restitution, and wrote many works about the subject including a casebook (with Jack Dawson) used in the teaching of restitution, a four-volume work on restitution, an article on the history of restitution which appeared in the International Encyclopedia of Comparative Law, and other articles that appeared in various law journals.
He served on several Law School committees, including the Academic Standards Committee (1970 - 1972) and the Library Advisory Committee (1965 - 1969; committee chair, 1966 - 1969). He was also a member of the Board of Governors of Residence Halls from 1957 to 1960, during which time the board was dealing with problems relating to the integration of the residence halls.
After retiring in 1978, Palmer continued to teach both at the university and as a guest lecturer at other law schools. He also continued to do research and produce scholarly articles throughout the 1980s. George Palmer died on May 10, 1994.
The George E. Palmer collection primarily contains notes and materials that Palmer used in teaching his classes. Several of his writings, as well as various pieces of correspondence that give insight into his research interests and personal character (especially his correspondence with Jack Dawson), can be found scattered throughout the collection. The collection is divided into four series: Trusts and Estates, Restitution, Guest Lecturing, and Topical Files.
Subjects:
Afro-American law students--Michigan.; Black Action Movement (University of Michigan); Black Law Students Alliance.; Coffey, Hobart R., 1896-1969.; Durfee, Edgar, 1882-1958.; Kauper, Paul, 1907-1974.; Law--Study and teaching--Michigan.; Law teachers--Michigan.; Mistake (Law)--Michigan.; Restitution--Michigan.; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Un-American Activities.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; University of Michigan--Law School.Law School.
Contributors:
Dawson, John P., 1902-1985.
- Trusts and Estates
  Trusts and Estates consists primarily of the lecture notes and materials that Palmer used in teaching the Trusts and Estates I class at the law school. The series also includes copies of the exams he used in this class, most of which include Palmer's handwritten answers to the questions. The Articles subseries contains three of his articles, correspondence with various publishers, and a sample of his research notes.
  - Class Lecture Materials
    - Chapter 1-Intestacy, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Chapter 2-Execution of Wills (Box 1)
    - Chapter 3-Revocation, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Chapter 4-Time Gap (Box 1)
    - Chapter 5-Forced Share (Box 1)
    - Chapter 6-Mistake and Ambiguity (Box 1)
    - Chapter 7-Trust as Property Arrangement (Box 1)
    - Chapter 8-Intent (Box 1)
    - Chapter 10-Beneficiary Restraints (Box 1)
    - Chapter 11
      - Formalities (Stat. Frauds) (Box 1)
      - Formalities (St. Wills) (Box 1)
    - Chapter 12-Charity (Box 1)
    - Chapter 14-Constructive Trust (Box 1)
    - Chapter 15
      - Section 1 (Box 1)
      - Section 2-Principal and Income (Box 1)
      - Section 3-Creditors' Claims (Box 1)
  - Exams
    - 1949-1961 (Box 1)
    - 1963-1980 (Box 1)
  - Articles
    - Incorporation Article I, 1951-1958 (Box 1)
    - Incorporation Article II, circa 1960 (Box 1)
    - Indefiniteness Article-Misc., 1962-1963; 1981 (Box 1)
    - Indefiniteness Article-Baden's Trusts, circa 1970s (Box 1)
    - Dependent relative Revocation Article, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Materials
    - Michigan Probate Code, 1978 (Box 2)
    - Supplement No. 1, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1980 (Box 2)
    - Seminar-Fix Correspondence, 1970-1975 (Box 2)
- Restitution
  The Restitution series contains materials from Palmer's courses on restitution. The materials for his main course on restitution (a three-credit hour course) are divided into two parts, one taught using the first edition of the course textbook, and the other taught using the 1969 edition. Articles that Palmer published and used in teaching this course can be found in the following four folders: Chapter 7, Contracts - D. in Default; Chapter 10, Mistake in Integration; and Chapter 10, Mistake in Performance (all 1969 Edition), and Chapter 5, Section 2 - Misunderstanding (first edition). The series also includes copies of the exams he used for his restitution class, as well as written comments by Palmer about some of the student research projects that were done for this course. There is also one folder containing correspondence about and some of the materials from the shorter, two-credit hour restitution course. The Articles subseries contains two of his articles and related correspondence. The Seminar subseries includes notes and other materials Palmer used for his class lectures, as well as copies of assignments he gave to the class and notes about relevant information pertaining to the solutions of these assignments.
  - Class Lecture Materials
    - Correspondence and Materials for Two-Hour Course, 1966-1984 (Box 2)
    - Edition, 1969
      - Course Outline (Box 2)
      - Chapter 1 (Box 2)
      - Chapter 2-Volunteer (Box 2)
      - Chapter 3-Tort (Box 2)
      - Chapter 4-Ideas, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Chapter 5, 5 folders (Box 2)
      - Chapter 6 (Box 2)
      - Chapter 7
        - Contracts-D. in Default (Box 2)
        - P. in Default (Box 2)
        - Impossibility (Box 2)
        - Unenforceable Costs (Box 2)
      - Chapter 8-Illegality (Box 2)
      - Chapter 9-Conditions, etc (Box 2)
      - Chapter 10
        - Mistake-Basic Assumptions (Box 2)
        - Mistake in Integration (Box 2)
        - Mistake in Performance (Box 2)
      - Supplementary Materials
        - Casebook (Box 2)
        - Casebook Revision (Box 2)
        - Mimeographed Materials, 1973; 1975 (Box 2)
        - Assignment Guides (Box 2)
        - Special Assignments (Box 2)
    - First Edition
      - Course Outline, 1950 (Box 2)
      - Chapter 1
        - Law I (Box 2)
        - Law II (Box 2)
        - Equity (Box 2)
      - Chapter 2
        - Section 1-Remedies for Fraud (Box 2)
        - Section 2-Restoration by P (Box 2)
        - Section 3-Election (Box 2)
        - Section 4 (Box 2)
      - Chapter 3
        - Section 1A-D. in Default, 2 folders (Box 2)
        - Section 1B-P. in Default (Box 2)
        - Section 2-Impossibility (Box 2)
        - Section 3-Unforceable Agreements (Box 2)
      - Chapter 4 (Box 2)
      - Chapter 5
        - Section 1-Mistake-Basic Assumptions, 2 folders (Box 2)
        - Section 2-Misunderstanding (Box 2)
        - Section 3-Mistake in Integration (Box 2)
        - Section 4-Mistake in Performance (Box 2)
      - Chapter 6 (Box 2)
      - Chapter 7-Insanity (Box 2)
  - Exams and Student Research
    - Exams, 1951-1966 (Box 3)
    - Exams, 1967-1981 (Box 3)
    - Exam Question Possibilities, 1956-1975 (Box 3)
    - Student Research, 1971 (Box 3)
  - Articles
    - Ohio State Article, 1958-1959 (Box 3)
    - Hastings, 1967-1968 (Box 3)
    - "The Effect of Misunderstanding on Contract Formation and Reformation Under the Restatement of Contracts Second,", 1965-1967 (Box 3)
  - Seminar
    - Class Lecture Materials
      - Course Outlines and Schedules, 1956-1966 (Box 3)
      - Course Outline, 1972 (Box 3)
      - Choice of Remedies (Box 3)
      - Volunteer, 1956 (Box 3)
      - Chapter 8-Duress I (Box 3)
      - Mistake of Law (Box 3)
      - Mistake-General, 1957-1964 (Box 3)
      - Mistake, 1964 (Box 3)
    - Assignments
      - Land Contract Problem, 1956 (Box 3)
      - Mistake Bid Problem, 1956; 1958 (Box 3)
      - Mistake Title Problem, 1957 (Box 3)
      - Chapter 8-Duress III, 1958 (Box 3)
      - Prior Assignments, 1966-1967 (Box 3)
      - Mistake-Reformation (Blay v. Pollard), 1966 (Box 3)
      - Mistake-Payment Where a Defense, 1966 (Box 3)
      - Mistake-Basic A-Mutual and Unilateral, 1966 (Box 3)
      - Mistake in Gifts, 1958 (Box 3)
      - Research Topics, 1972 (Box 3)
- Guest Lecturing
  Guest Lecturing includes correspondence and book reviews relating to a series of three lectures on mistake that Palmer gave at Ohio State University in 1961. These lectures were printed as a book entitled Mistake and Unjust Enrichment. The series also contains classroom materials and exams that Palmer used at three of the schools where he taught Trusts and Estates for a semester as a guest lecturer (UCLA in 1961, Hastings College of the Law in 1979, and University of Florida in 1979). These files also include some correspondence.
  - Ohio Lectures on Mistake
    - Correspondence and Book Reviews, 1959-1971 (Box 3)
    - Sheahan's Follies, 1962 (Box 3)
  - U.C.L.A
    - Trusts and Estates I, 1961 (Box 3)
    - Course Material and Correspondence, 1961-1962 (Box 3)
  - Hastings College of the Law
    - Correspondence
      - 1973-1975 (Box 3)
      - 1977-1978 (Box 3)
    - Exam, 1979 (Box 3)
    - Class Supplementary Materials, 1979 (Box 3)
  - University of Florida
    - Exam, 1979 (Box 3)
    - Class Supplementary Materials, 1979 (Box 3)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files series contains correspondence, notes and materials from different law school and university committees he served on, memos he wrote, and miscellaneous teaching materials. Of particular interest are the files pertaining to African American students, which document some of the problems and struggles relating to the integration of the law school. Also of interest is the Civil Liberties folder, which contains newspaper clippings and other documents regarding the removal of three University of Michigan professors due to their political beliefs during the McCarthy era. There are also folders containing information on some of the other law professors at the university that Palmer knew well and wrote eulogies for when they died (Hobart Coffey, Jack Dawson, Edgar Durfee, and Paul Kauper). The folders "Class Schedules" and "Grades - My Tabulation" contain lists of the classes that Palmer taught at the University. Some of Palmer's earlier writings during his studies at the Columbia University School of Law can be found in the "Columbia" and "Jurisprudence" folders.
  - Academic Appointment, 1965 (Box 3)
  - Academic Standards Committee
    - 1969-1971 (Box 3)
    - 1972 (Box 3)
  - Administrative Law-Paper, 1939 (Box 3)
  - Antoine's Follies, 1975 (Box 3)
  - Association of American Law Schools, 1948 (Box 3)
  - Australia, 1982-1990 (Box 3)
  - Bar Exams, 1951-1959 (Box 3)
  - Black Action Movement, 1970 (Box 4)
  - Black Law Students Alliance, 1971 (Box 4)
  - Black Students I, 1968-1969 (Box 4)
  - Black Students II, 1968-1974 (Box 4)
  - Board of Governors-Racial Discrimination, 1957-1958 (Box 4)
  - Case Club, 1967-1969 (Box 4)
  - Civil Liberties-Clardy Investigating Committee, 1954-1955; 1989 (Box 4)
  - Class Schedules, 1946-1975 (Box 4)
  - Coffey, Hobart, 1969 (Box 4)
  - Columbia
    - Essays, circa 1940 (Box 4)
    - Thesis, 1940 (Box 4)
  - Commercial Code Article-Correspondence, 1949-1950 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence
    - 1945-1958 (Box 4)
    - 1959-1966 (Box 4)
    - 1967-1991 (Box 4)
  - Curriculum Changes, 1948-1968 (Box 4)
  - Curriculum Studies on Restitution and Trusts and Estates I, circa 1950s (Box 4)
  - Dawson, Jack, 1983-1986 (Box 4)
  - Durfee, Edgar, circa 1950-1986 (Box 4)
  - Examinations, 1949-1954 (Box 4)
  - Gifts to Law School, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Grades-My Tabulation, 1949-1980 (Box 4)
  - Graduate Students' Research, 1954-1959 (Box 4)
  - International Encyclopedia of Comparative Law Article, 1982-1990 (Box 4)
  - Interpretation, Seminar on, circa 1965 (Box 4)
  - Jurisprudence, 1937-1941 (Box 4)
  - Kauper, Paul, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Law School-Miscellaneous, 1957-1963 (Box 4)
  - Legal Education Seminar, 1967 (Box 4)
  - Library Committee
    - 1965-1966 (Box 4)
    - 1966-1967 (Box 4)
    - 1967-1968 (Box 4)
    - 1968-1969 (Box 4)
    - Building Plans, 1963-1966 (Box 4)
  - Library-Memos from Palmer, 1962-1985 (Box 4)
  - Memos from Palmer, 1955-1973 (Box 4)
  - Michigan Law Review, 1947-1964 (Box 4)
  - Office Space, 1966-1969 (Box 4)
  - Planning Committee, circa 1950s (Box 4)
  - Reunion-50th, 1981 (Box 4)
  - Stenographic Help-Memos, 1965-1966 (Box 4)
  - Student Discipline-University, 1970-1971 (Box 4)
  - Student Power, 1969 (Box 4)
  - Tenure Appointments, 1966-1972 (Box 4)
  - Texas-Summer, 1969 (Box 4)